Guide to the North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company Archives, 1850-2008 and undated, bulk 1898-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
- Company Offices Series, 1850, 1898-2008 and undated, bulk 1920-2000, (83 boxes plus oversize containers)
  - Office of the President Subseries, 1903-2002 and undated, bulk from 1950s-1990s [RESTRICTED]
    - William J. Kennedy, III, (7 boxes)
      - Company Business/Personnel
        - NCM long range planning manual - 1st draft, 1973
        - NCM Moving to...Mutual Plaza, 1965
        - Photos - WJK III, Heritage room, undated
        - Report on examination of NCM, 1962, 1968, 1983, 1986, (4 folders)
        - Time capsule placement ceremony, 1963 Oct. 20
        - Claim settlement practices in Virginia, 1978 (Box 38)
        - Documents relating to the reinsurance of North American Insurance Company, 1974-1980
        - Insurance Certificates of Authority, 1977
        - Miscellaneous company business, 1977 and undated
        - Notes, 1984-1986
        - Releases, agreements, and contracts for reinsurance, 1970-1975
        - Various personal insurance policies and invoices for W.J. Kennedy, III, 1946, 1953-1965, (3 folders)
        - Personal letter to Kennedy from mother and father, William Kennedy Jr., on vacation trip to New Mexico, 1958 Sept. 24
        - Various NCM committee agendas and plans, 1988-1989
      - Correspondence
        Materials include chronologically-ordered internal and external correspondence with the Office of the President under William J. Kennedy, III. Also includes various NCM memoranda.
        - Correspondence-External, 1973-1974, 1982-1983, 1988-1990, (2 folders) (Box 39)
        - Internal correspondence and memos, 1972-1974, 1978-1982
        - Essence magazine correspondence for possible investment, 1973
        - Goodloe policy inquiry and correspondence, 1947-1948, 1988
        - Insurance Holding Company Act, Linville Roach, 1987-1989, (2 folders)
        - National Employers Security Trust, 1976
        - Virginia Mutual, 1975
      - Other Insurance Companies
        Contains material relating to annual/financial statements, contracts, and correspondence with other insurance companies that were associated with NC Mutual in terms of mergers and reinsurance.
        - Annual Statement of the Southern Life Insurance Company, 1983 (Box 38)
        - All American Assurance Company annual statements and minutes, 1974-1976, (2 folders)
        - American Citizens Life Insurance Corporation information and annual statement, 1978-1979, (2 folders)
        - Bradford's Industrial Insurance Co. annual statement and examination, 1977-1981 (Box 40)
        - Chicago Metropolitan Mutual Assurance Company:
          - Annual statements, examinations, business records, 1965-1975, 1978, (4 folders)
          - Merger agreement, circa 1973-1974, (2 folders)
          - Policy samples, undated
        - Mammoth Insurance Company merger, 1985
        - Mutual Benefit Society of Baltimore City contract information, merger, and historical sketch, 1977-1978, (2 folders)
        - NC Mutual budget statements and merger information, 1978, (2 folders)
        - New South Life Insurance Company records, 1978
        - North Carolina Insurance Code and purchasing/selling of other insurance companies, 1978
        - Other insurance companies annual statements, 1975-1986
        - Provident Home Industrial Insurance Company merger and miscellaneous info, 1974-1975, 1981, (2 folders) (Box 41)
        - Pyramid Life Insurance, 1969-1970, 1975
        - Southern Aid Life Insurance annual statement, 1986
        - Southern Life Insurance Company, 1977
        - Union Protective Life Insurance Company business records, 1973-1975
        - United Mutual Insurance Company of NY annual statement and information, 1985-1987, (3 folders)
        - Universal Life Insurance Company of Memphis annual statement, 1979
        - Various merged companies' financial information, 1975-1977
        - Virginia Mutual Benefit Life Insurance Company:
          - Annual statement, 1984
          - Acquisition, 1985-1988, (2 folders)
          - Miscellaneous files, 1988
        - Winston Mutual Life Insurance Company annual statements, 1973, 1975, 1983
      - Other Organizations
        Includes material relating to business meetings, memoranda, and other miscellaneous information concerning organizations outside of North Carolina Mutual with which William J. Kennedy, III and NCM were affiliated. Material is organized alphabetically.
        - American Capital Life Insurance Company, 1986-1988 (Box 42)
        - American Citizens Life Insurance portfolio summary, 1979
        - Chicago Metropolitan:
          - Employee information, 1969, 1972
          - Labor union agreement, 1970
          - Merger information, contracts, 1974
          - Significant financials, reports, 1973
        - Coinsurance agreement between American Capital Life Insurance Co. and Citizens Security Life Insurance Co., 1980
        - Deloitte, Haskins, and Sells, 1980 Dec. 12
        - NC Association of Life Insurance Companies, 1985-1990 and undated, (5 folders)
        - Opportunities Industrialization Centers, 1986-1989, (2 folders)
        - Virginia Mutual Life Insurance Co., 1988
        - Winston Mutual Life Insurance Co. merger information and finances, 1974, 1977, 1984
    - Bert Collins, (23 boxes)
      Collins served as the President of NC Mutual from 1990-2003. Prior to his role as president, Collins served as an Executive Vice President for the company. Includes documents dating from when he first joined the company in the 1970s through until near the end of his tenure as president, with the majority of the material dating from 1985-1994. The contents are organized into four categories: budget/finance, company business/personnel, correspondence, and other organizations. Some personnel records were removed to Personnel Subseries. Arranged in rough alphabetical order or in original order as received.
      - Budget/Finance
        Contains material relating to financial aspects of NCM company business. Examples include company audits, budgets, financial reports, bills for service and pension account reports. Organized alphabetically by folder title.
        - Budgets (proposed), 1988, 1990 (Box 43)
        - Business plans and budgets, Insurance OPS, 1990
        - Check requisitions, bills for service, receipts ledger entries, 1990-1994, (4 folders)
        - Claims, 1988-1990
        - Comparative Statement of Budget and Actual Income and Disbursements for 1991 Sept. 30
        - Corporate business plan, 1988 Nov. 16
        - Employee Pension Account reports, 1987
        - First Capital Life payments, 1986-1989
        - First Capital Life and E.F. Hutton business records (financial), 1986-1991
        - Internal audit, budget, reports, clearing checks, general finance, 1986-1992, (5 folders)
        - Internal audit, budget, reports, clearing checks, 1992-1994, (2 folders) (Box 44)
        - Mechanic and Farmer's Bank statement, 1971-1972
        - Ostine Swan - Review Audit Plan, 1995
        - PW Trust Company, 1994
        - Custom Transaction Listings, 1990 July-Nov., 1992 Aug. 13, (2 folders) (Box 66)
        - Group Reinsurance Contingency Reserves, 1990
        - Premium income by week, 1990
        - Securities Committee minutes, 1987-1990
      - Company business/Personnel
        Contains material relating to non-financial aspects of the company business, including but not limited to matters relating to personnel. Documents are organized alphabetically. Non-NCM printed material is located in the "N" section and includes material such as various business articles, the Durham Rotary Bulletin, and photocopies of newspaper clippings. Similar material can be found in the Printed Material Series.
        [Confidential material has been removed to Personnel Subseries and is closed for 75 years from date of creation of most recent record or 2074.]
        - 20th anniversary of Mutual Plaza, 1968-1988 (Box 45)
        - Ad hoc committee to study use of Home Office facilities, 1976
        - A.J. Rivers retirement, 1990
        - Asa T. Spaulding Insurance Hall of Fame candidacy information, 1943-1953, 1961-1971, 1990-1991
        - Bachrach Studio - Presidential photo, 1991
        - Claims, 1988-1990
        - Collins promotion congrats and clippings, 1987
        - Collins speeches and remarks, 1991
        - Compensation Task Force, 1987
        - Complaints, 1988-1992
        - Conflict of Interest forms, 1994
        - Control Environment questionnaire, undated
        - Copies of memos to Board of Directors, 1980-1983
        - Data Processing Project 4, 1987 Mar.
        - Data Processing Task Force, 1989 May-July
        - Directions and Goals: Field Operations, 1984
        - Disaster Plans - letters, 1973
        - District mergers, 1988
        - Dr. Charles Watts, 1987
        - Duties of the System Coordinator, undated
        - Electronic Data Systems, 1989-1990
        - Employee and Management evaluation, analysis, and improvement, 1985, (9 of 13 folders)
        - Employee and Management evaluation, analysis, and improvement, 1985, (4 of 13 folders) (Box 46)
        - Employee personal computers, 1985-1987, undated
        - Employee Performance Reports material, undated
        - Environmental Task Force, 1989 May-July
        - Field Committee, 1986-1987, (2 folders)
        - Field Accounting System, 1982-1990, (5 folders)
        - Founders' Day, 1987
        - Furniture and fixtures, 1984-1989, undated
        - Goodloe policy, Parrish policy, 1990
        - Hay Management Consultants report and recommendations for Incentive Program, 1985 Nov.
        - Historical documents, 1989 (Box 47)
        - Home Office appointments, 1990-1993
        - John Tyler Caldwell Award for Humanities Program (Honoree: John Hope Franklin), 1991
        - Management Development program, 1985-1986
        - Memorex maintenance agreement, 1985
        - Merger of Mutual Community Savings Bank with Greensboro National Bank, 1994
        - Miscellaneous company business, 1989-1994, (5 folders)
        - NCM business plans for 1989-1992, 1989
        - NCM Life Communications sale of Williamsburg, Va. radio stations, 1985
        - NC Mutual Re-engineering project, 1994
        - Non-NCM printed material: Performance Appraisals that Measure Up, 1985
        - Non-NCM printed material: UN Bio: Joseph Nanven Garba (Nigeria), circa 1989
        - Non-NCM printed material, 1989-1994, (5 folders)
        - Office maps, 1986 and undated (Box 48)
        - Orphan photo, undated
        - Personnel:
          [All of these files have been removed to the Personnel Subseries and are closed for 75 years from date of creation of most recent record or 2074.]
          - Pension Fund Manager, 1990 (Box 48)
          - Pension Investment, 1986-1988 (Box 48)
          - Pensions and Retirement, 1986 (Box 48)
          - Pension Retirement Plan Committee - appointments and resignations, 1991 (Box 48)
          - 12th floor personnel, 1988 (Box 48)
          - Absenteeism and Tardiness policy, 1986 (Box 48)
          - Changes in assignment and promotion, 1979-1989 and undated (Box 48)
          - Craig Page - RDU Airport, 1990 (Box 48)
          - Letters of recommendation, 1974-1990 and undated (Box 48)
          - Personnel matters, 1988-1994, (5 folders) (Box 48)
          - Org charts and personnel listings, 1990 and undated (Box 48)
          - Reference letters, 1991 Sept.-Oct. (Box 48)
          - Salary policy and examination, 1986 (Box 48)
          - Sexual Harassment policy, undated (Box 48)
          - Suggestion plan, 1985-1990 and undated (Box 48)
        - Planning, 1989 (Box 48)
        - Policy approval material, 1983-1989 and undated (Box 48)
        - Press release, 1988 (Box 48)
        - Program to conserve NAIC business, 1980 (Box 48)
        - Retirement and Welfare Plan summary annual reports, 1988-1989 (Box 48)
        - Revoked CPA license, 1983 (Box 48)
        - Planning documents and reports: staffing plans, Underwriting and Actuarial Depts., Human Resources, 1980s-1990s (Box 48.1)
        - Retirement plans: Great West Life payments, 1989-1991, Capital Life documents, executive compensation, 1989 (Box 48.1)
        - Profitability Task Force: (Box 49)
          - NC Mutual annual statement, 1982
          - Minutes and agenda, 1983-1984, (2 folders)
          - Studies:
            - Agency, 1983-1984, (2 folders)
            - Controller and misc., 1983
            - Correspondence, 1983
            - Direct group, 1983
            - Executive Committee recommendations, 1983
            - Financial data, 1983
            - Hospitalization - Employee benefits, 1983
            - Re-insurance and EDP, 1983
        - Speeches: (Box 50)
          - Boy Scout Troop 55, 1992
          - District offices, 1975, 1980-1990, and undated, (2 folders)
          - Dr. Donna Benson, Vita - Introduction, 1992
          - Durham Business and Professional Chain banquet - Kenneth Chenault, 1991
          - Durham Business and Professional Chain banquet - Tony Brown, 1992
          - Speech file, 1990-1991 and undated
          - Goldsboro district home office visit, 1992 June 25
          - Good Idea speech material, undated
          - Greetings, 1991
          - Impact of violence on the business community, undated
          - Introduction for Dr. Anderson, Black Labor, White Wealth, 1994
          - Health Care, 1992 Nov. 18
          - Life/70 training, 1992 June 19
          - Mel Watt introduction, 1993 Aug. 1
          - Miscellaneous speech material, 1991-1998 and undated
          - Receptions, 1990-1991
        - Sayre and Sayre, 1989 (Box 51)
        - Southwood Landscaping contract, 1982
        - Suggestion Committee, Good Idea campaign, 1991
        - Survey results, 1988
        - Survey of mutual life insurance companies, 1986
        - Team Leader Task Force, 1988, (14 folders)
        - Telecommunications, 1983-1986
        - Today's mail, 1993 Feb. 9
        - Board meeting, 1985, (3 folders) (Box 66)
        - Employee Agreements, 1974-1988 and undated
        - Employee Group Health Plan, 1984-1988
        - Equipment lease file, et al., 1985-1986
        - Miscellaneous documents, 1990 and undated
        - Collins, Bar exam, 1970
        - Rolling Hills - Offer to purchase and contract, 1990
        - Salary study, 1970, 1977, 1984
        - Whetstone Editorial Board, 1988
      - Correspondence
        Materials include chronologically-ordered internal and external correspondence with the Office of the President and the Office of the Executive Vice President under Bert Collins. Also includes North Carolina Mutual committees' meeting minutes and information, and NCM memoranda.
        - Correspondence-External: (Box 52)
          - 1978 June, 1984 Feb., 1987-1990, (4 folders)
          - Collins promotion congratulations, thank you's and announcement addresses, 1990
          - 1991-1994, (5 folders)
        - General solicitations, 1989-1994, (10 folders) (Box 53)
        - Internal memoranda and meetings: (Box 54)
          - 1984-1988
          - NCM Board of Directors meeting, 1989 May 24, (2 folders)
          - NCM Board of Directors meeting, 1989 July 26, (2 folders)
          - 1989-1994, (4 folders)
        - Correspondence-Internal: (Box 55)
          - 1989-1991 and undated, (2 folders)
          - Letters to District Managers, 1991 Oct.
          - 1992-1994
        - Other correspondence:
          - Attorney Charles McClain, 1994
          - Black Directory information and business plan, 1990-1992
          - Correspondence with Black Enterprise, 1993 Mar.-Apr.
          - Charles Ray - proposal, 1994
          - C.C. Spaulding papers - Duke Library, 1999-2000
          - Department of Insurance - various states, 1990-1994
          - Dollars and Sense 1993 Jan. issue, solicitation and correspondence
          - Draft letter to A.M. Best Co. from Bert Collins, 2002
          - EEOC Notice of Charge of Discrimination, 1989
          - Government departments and agencies, 1989-1994
          - Motivational sales letters, 1993
          - Shaw University campaign, 1992
          - The Continuum Co. correspondence, 1982-1989
          - Tillinghast correspondence, 1989-1990
        - Correspondence and memoranda, 1990-1991 (Box 66)
      - Other Organizations
        Includes material relating to business meetings, memoranda, retreats, and other miscellaneous information concerning organizations outside of NCM with which Bert Collins and NCM were affiliated. Connections to these organizations range from giving philanthropically to holding a seat on a Board of Executives. Material is organized alphabetically.
        - Air Atlanta, 1986-1987 (Box 56)
        - American Citizens Life Corporation, 1985 Nov. 12, 1988-1990, 1994, (2 folders)
        - American Citizens Life Corporation - Board of Directors meeting, annual stockholders meeting announcement, 1991 Apr.
        - American Council of Life Insurance: Life Insurance Company Quality Efforts survey, completed by Charkes Blackmon, 1992
        - American Council of Life Insurance: Proposed regulation, 1990, (7 folders)
        - Boys and Girls Club, 1987-1991, (1-2 of 4 folders)
        - Boys and Girls Club: 1987-1991, (3-4 of 4 folders) (Box 57)
        - Boys and Girls Club: National Council Annual meeting, 1991 (Box 57)
        - Regional meeting, 1994 Apr. 19 (Box 57)
        - CLG, Inc., 1985-1987
        - Deloitte and Touche, 1984-1990, (2 folders)
        - Duke Hypertension Center - Community Advisory Board, 1994 June 25
        - Duke University Fuqua School of Business, 1987-1989, (2 folders)
        - Ernst and Young (Ernst and Whinney), 1983-1990, (2 folders)
        - External meetings, symposiums, and retreats, 1990-1992, (2 folders)
        - External memos, reports, and general info, 1989-1990
        - External memos, reports, and general info, 1990-1994, (10 folders) (Box 58)
        - External memos, reports, and general info, 1994, (4 folders) (Box 59)
        - Greater Triangle Community Foundation: 1991, (2 folders)
        - Greater Triangle Community Foundation: Board of Directors, 1991
        - Greater Triangle Community Foundation: Finance Committee meeting, 1991 Nov. 7, (2 folders)
        - Greater Triangle Community Foundation: Finance Committee minutes, 1991
        - Guardsmen, 1994 (Box 60)
        - Insurance Achievement - John Allen, 1987-1989, (2 folders)
          [Five audiocassettes removed to Recordings Series.]
        - J. Brown, Pro Care Insurance Services, Inc., 1994
        - Leadership Training Institute and Civil Rights Reunion, 1990 Aug. 15-19
        - Legislative and Salary Study Commission report, 1990
        - LIC Board Meeting - Chicago, 1994 Sept. 24-25
        - Major Campaign Review Board, 1991
        - NC Business Council, 1991
        - NC Center for Nonprofits, 1994
        - North Carolina Airports Association annual meetings, 1991
        - North Carolina Amateur Sports Board of Directors, 1987-1991
        - Raison D'Etre Club, 1970-1972
        - Raleigh Durham Airport, 1990
        - Richard Genz - Z. Smith Reynolds Foundation, 1992-1993
        - Total Quality Education, 1994
        - UDI/CDC Board meeting, 1994 Sept. 28
        - United Way of Greater Durham Loaned Executive Training, 1992 Aug. 17
        - Wachovia Board meeting, 1994 Apr. 15
        - Who's Who in America, 1992-1994
        - NCM Capital: (Box 61)
          - Acquisition, 1991, (5 folders) (Box 61)
          - Attorney's fees, 1991 (Box 61)
          - Harper, Wiggins, and Co. Accountants proposal to serve, 1990 (Box 61)
          - Information regarding purchase, 1991 (Box 61)
          - Items due from lease, 1991 (Box 61)
          - Management Group business records and information, 1988-1991, (3 folders) (Box 61)
          - By-laws, 1991 (Box 61)
          - Compensation data, 1991 (Box 61)
          - 1991 (Box 61)
          - Corporate meetings, 1990 (Box 61)
          - Information, 1990-1991, (2 folders) (Box 61)
          - Information packets, circa 1988 (Box 62)
          - Executive Committee meeting, 1991 (Box 62)
          - NCM Board resolutions, 1991 (Box 62)
          - Note purchases, 1991 (Box 62)
          - Quarterly report, 1990 (Box 62)
          - Stock and notes, audit info request, 1986-1991 (Box 62)
          - United Asset Management annual report, 1990 (Box 62)
        - North Carolina Central University: (Box 63)
          - Academic Affairs annual report, 1990-1991
          - Board of Trustees, 1988-1994, (7 folders)
          - Board of Trustees agendas and meetings, 1990
          - Board of Trustees info, 1989-1990
          - Board of Trustees information for Collins, 1990, (2 of 3 folders)
        - North Carolina Central University: (Box 64)
          - Board of Trustees information for Collins, 1990, (1 of 3 folders)
          - Budget info and case study for the Board of Trustees, 1990
          - Business Associates Program, 1988-1990
          - DeJarmon, 1992 Apr.
          - Miscellaneous, 1987-1991, (2 folders)
          - NCCU Foundation, 1983, (5 folders)
          - NCCU Foundation report, 1991 Apr. 12
          - Open House, 1992
        - North Carolina Central University: (Box 65)
          - Records from UNC Board of Governors, 1989-1991, (2 folders)
          - Records from The University of North Carolina - the 1989 Conference on Trusteeship
          - Printed Material - Feasibility Study, 1984
          - Printed Material - NCCU Catalog, 1988-1990
          - School of Law - Board of Visitors, 1975-1990, (2 folders)
          - Search Committee, 1991
          - Trustee Collins, 1991 Apr.
          - UNC Board of Governors, 1993
          - UNC-CH campus visitation, 1994 Oct. 14
        - American Citizens Life Insurance Corporation, 1987-1988 (Box 66)
        - Mutual Savings and Loan, 1988-1992 and undated
    - Office of the President Oversize Material
      - Annual statement and clippings, 1965, 1988 (Box OV1)
      - New York Life Insurance Company annual statement, 1959 (Box OV2)
      - Clippings, 1959
      - Clippings, 1987-1989
      - Clippings, 1994, (2 folders)
      - Life/70 Proposal, 1979 Jan. 3
      - Retiree information, floor plan markups, 1970, circa 1990 (Box OV4)
      - Fifty leading industrial life companies, 1952 (Box OV8)
      - Financial statement, casualty statements and reports, 1931, 1961-1965
      - Employer year end reports, 1971-1972
      - Asa T. Spaulding clipping, 1990
      - Floor plans, 1986
      - FAS master schedule, circa 1992
      - The Independent, 1999 Feb. 10-16
      - Newspaper clippings, 1990-1991
      - Carpet layout, 1987 (Box OV10)
      - Merrick-Moore Scholarship clippings, 1935-1936 (Box OV38)
      - 1982 net incomes by state and Analysis of operations by lines of business, 1982
  - Personnel Files Subseries, 1950s-1990s
    Files on employees of NC Mutual originally located in the Office of the President Subseries, chiefly created from the 1950s through the 1990s.
    [The Personnel files Subseries is CLOSED to access for 75 years from date of creation of most recent record, or 2074.]
    - Personnel Files (Box 67-68)
  - Public Relations Subseries, 1911-2008 and undated, (13 boxes and oversize containers)
    Material in files chiefly documents activities such as advertising, publications and printing, and community relations projects undertaken by North Carolina Mutual. The Photographic Material Series also houses an extensive collections of images used by the Public Relations Department in publications such as The Whetstone.